John Roberts Papers
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
- 3. Travel Film Production Materials, 1947
  - Travel Program Promotional Materials (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Switzerland Today" and "This is New England" by John Roberts (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Assignment Switzerland" presented by John Roberts (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John Roberts presents "Highlights of New England" (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John Roberts presents "Norway and the Modern Vikings" (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John Roberts presents "Norway and the Modern Vikings" (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John Roberts presents "Delightful Denmark" (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John Roberts presents "Holland and the Amazing Dutch" (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Valley of the Rhine" by John W. Roberts (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John Roberts presents "The Majestic Rhine" (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Our 25th season" presented by World TravelVenture Films hosted by Ruth and LeRoy Crooks (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "The 1990 World Wide Passport Film Series" (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Travel Film Booklets (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "An Adventure in International Understanding in Six World Capital" (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Stanley Warner Corporation presents the Lowell Thomas Production "Seven Wonders of the World ...as seen through the greatest wonder" Cinerama (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Michael Todd presents Lowell Thomas, Jr. (in person) in "Out of This World" A journey to Lhasa, Tibet (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 4. Published Materials, 1945 - 1981
  Series contains materials that were published that pertain to John Roberts or Lowell Thomas. This includes advertisements that John Roberts was the photographer for, and newspaper clippings. The newspaper clippings consists of both original clippings and photocopies of clippings
  - Advertisements from the "Debutante Register", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Skol, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Revlon, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Chen Yu, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Trifari, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The Waldorf-Astoria, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Photocopies (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Lowell Thomas is Enthusiastic Over Alaska Vacation, August 14 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Outposts" applauded by thousands now available for national release (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Leaves for Near East on Movie Assignment, March 2, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bearded, burned, Lowell Thomas is back from ice cap (2), August 12, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photocopy of clippings: 1. Bearded, burned, Lowell Thomas is back from ice cap 2. Leaves for Near East on Movie Assignment 3. Lowell Thomas is Enthusiastic Over Alaska Vacation, 4. "Outposts" applauded by thousands now available for national release (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photocopy, "Born to Ski" soars to New Heights (x2), January 6, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Television guide, January 18, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photocopy of two clippings, 1. Roberts' Holland Film Draws crowd of 8,900 2. Travelogue on Norway Draws More Than 9,000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photocopy of two clippings, 1. Color Travelogue superb, beautiful 2. Something Rockin' in 'Denmark', February 1, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Young Photographers Will Make First Travelogue for CimemaScope (original and copy) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Junior Thomas' Tibet Superb (original and copy) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photocopy, Mrs. Lowell Thomas, Sr. is dead at eighty-one, February 19, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photocopy, Lowell Thomas Celebrates 83rd Birthday in Vail, April 11, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photocopy, Lowell Thomas: A living treasure in history (photocopy and original), October 17, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Lowell Thomas Remains a 'Young' Man at Age 80 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photocopy, Inland season Lowell Thomas, July 24, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Thomas: Pioneer newscaster dies, August 30, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - News Pioneer Lowell Thomas is Dead at 89 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - So Long, Lowell Thomas (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Persian Gulf Crisis: Blame It on Lawrence of Arabia, December 23, 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Gulf Crisis: Blame it on Lawrence of Arabia (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Untitled clippings (3) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Lowell Thomas is visitor at local studio (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - John Roberts' Ski Film Thrills Large Audience (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photocopy, new picutre on near east to be shown at lodge (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photocopy, Looking for More (Box 1, Folder 16)
- 5. Personal Materials, 1946 - 2006
  Series contains materials about John Roberts, including biographical notes and partial memoir started by John Roberts, obituaries for John Roberts, and John Roberts’ passports.
  - Biographical Notes and Partial Memoir (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Resume/Cover Letter John R. Roberts (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Biographical Notes, John W. Roberts (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Biography, John W. Roberts (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Biographical Notes, John W. Roberts (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - John W. Roberts - Bio (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Draft of Biographical Notes (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Memoir draft, I think I will write a book (original and copy) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Memoir draft (original and copy) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - John Roberts Obituary, February 2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Draft, Clay Ballou's obituary for John Roberts, February 2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Clay Ballou's obituary for John Roberts, February 2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Printed version of Clay Ballou's Obituary for John Roberts, February 2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Passport (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - John Roberts Passport, 1946 - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- 6. Photographs, 1934 - 1950
  Series six is divided into three subseries: 6.1 Photos of Lowell Thomas, 6.2 Career Photographs, and 6.3 Personal Photographs.
  - Subseries 6.1: Photos of Lowell Thomas
    Subseries has photos of Lowell Thomas in Alaska and Tibet, photos of Lowell Thomas, and signed headshots of Lowell Thomas
    - Lowell Thomas in Alaska (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Lowell Thomas on boat in front of iceberg (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Lowell Thomas and three other men, on tarmac in front of Rescue plane (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Lowell Thomas and three other men, on tarmac in front of Rescue plane (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Lowell Thomas and Rescue plane pilot on tarmac in front of Rescue plane (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Lowell Thomas and Rescue plane pilot on tarmac in front of Rescue plane (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lowell Thomas in Tibet (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Landscape photo of Tibet, building/compound on top of hill next to lake (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Dalai Lama at 16 years old, ceremony (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas Jr. with Tibetan monks in front of temple/compound. Inscription reads: "To Johnny, Who went with us deep into Tibet. Greetings from Lhasa. 1949. Lowell Thomas Sr. + Jr." (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - John Roberts with camera, with person posing for camera. (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Lowell Thomas and crew, standing on hilly landscape (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Lowell Thomas and two Tibetan men standing in front of piano (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lowell Thomas (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Lowell Thomas standing in group at formal event (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Lowell Thomas and another men standing in front of building (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Lowell Thomas speaking with camera men, two cameras and four men (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Lowell Thomas and two men in front of out building. Lowell Thomas Jr. is man on right(2) (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Lowell Thomas and wife, posing with another couple (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Lowell Thomas pointing at map for three other men (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Cut out portrait of Lowell Thomas in war correspondent uniform (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Signed Lowell Thomas Headshots (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Lowell Thomas at NBC microphone, inscription "Hi There Johnny! Lowell Thomas" (copy) (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Lowell Thomas resting head on hand, inscription "To my old friend, Johnny! Lowell Thomas" (Original and copy) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 6.2: Photographs from Careeer, 1946 - 1950
    Subseries contains photos taken during the course of John Roberts career and for travelogues, these includes photos from John’s Middle East trip, Holland, “Adventures in Skiing” and of Andrea Mead Lawrence, Squaw Valley Skiing Races, Thor Hyerdahl in Norway, and various models
    - Middle East Trip, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Building entrance and window, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Holy Sepulcher - Jewels of the Virgin Mary, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Ancient columns (x2), 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Tennis court with palm trees in background, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - John Roberts with camera, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Man standing on top mosque tower, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - John Roberts with camera and men in jeep, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Rock formation, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Palace, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Bow of boat, sailors working. Looking down from tower, castle walls with turrets, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Docked boat, Cushing Eells, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Large group of male students working around a table, chalkboard with flower diagrams in background, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - John Roberts climbing stairs to board plane, Air France, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Remains of old castle (2), 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Athletic fields on school grounds, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Landscape view, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Man and child, standing in doorway., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Portrait of man with gun inside a sangar, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Young man leaning against tree, school grounds in background, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Military parade, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Two men in taqiyah, structure with archways in background, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Scrapbook page with four images, 1. people walking on road, 2. people walking under covered road, 3. Mosque, 4. inside of ornate building, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Scrapbook page, eight images on front and description "Photos from John Roberts 1946 trip to the Middle East to film American Schools for Lowell Thomas", 2 images on back. Front images 1. person sitting on top of very large carved block, 2. ancient ruins with columns, 3. ancient ruins, large columns in background, 4. ancient ruins columns and header, 5. ancient ruins, large columns in background, 6. Ancient ruins, shrine, 7. Ancient ruins, archways 8. Ancient ruins, column and archways, decorated wall. Back, 1. Ancient ruins, intricate stone carving, 2. Ancient ruins, Corinthian column (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Holland (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Windmill (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Canal with bridge (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Windmills along river (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Windmill next to river (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Windmills along river (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Windmill next to river, flowers blooming (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Large ship. Rotterdam, city in background. Description of photo on back (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Two men in white outfits and hats carrying melons on slide (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Photos from "Adventures in Skiing" and of Andrea Mead Lawrence (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Group of people sitting in front of lodge, left to right: Janet Mead, Bill, Andy Mead, Dave Lawrence, Lal (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Skier going off a jump (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Karl Acket standing on skis that are stuck into the ground (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Andy Mead with St. Bernard dog (2) (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Portrait, Hannes Schneider "Mr. Ski" (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Portrait, Andy Mead (2) (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Andy Mead and Dave Lawrence (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Squaw Valley Skiing Races, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Ole Mikkelsen House, where John Roberts stayed during the races, February 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Marius Erikson, putting on gloves on slopes, March 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Marius Erikson and Mrs. Gary (Rickie) Cooper, holding skis on top slopes, March 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Joe Pennie of Marblehead, March 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - John and Junior, in front of lodge with camera (2), April 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Bus boys posing, left to right, Bart, unknown, Amil, Russ, April 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - John Roberts and Thor Hyerdahl in Norway (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Clayton Ballou and Thor Hyerdahl (2) (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Thor Hyerdahl holding book, Out of This World by Lowell Thomas, Jr. (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Portrait of Thor Hyerdahl (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - John Roberts Models (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Man in navy uniform, reading magazine on bed with records on shelf (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Man in navy unform, holding teacup, sitting on stool, in front of fireplace (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - People reading in front of building (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - People reading in front of building (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Man sitting in front of radio mixer (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Man working on radio mixer (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Man in bathing suit (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Man in bathing suit next to pool (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Man in army unifoom. Verso: A friend of John Robert, when he was in an Army film unit during World War 2. About 1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Train on trellis, Cog Railway, Mount Washington, New Hampshire, from John Robert's. "NEW ENGLAND" (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 6.3 Personal Photographs, 1934 - 1950
    Subseries contains photographs that were taken for personal use, this includes photographs of Clayton Ballou, John Roberts, vacation photos and other photos.
    - Clayton Ballou (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Teenage photo of Clayton Ballou (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou in plaid suit (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Signed portrait of Clayton Ballou (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou leaning against bolder near water (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou leaning against boulder in forest (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou on sailboat (2) (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and four friends, in bathing suits, sitting on blanket at the beach (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou sitting in beach chair (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and friend in bathing suits, sitting on towels holding a camera. Grounds of a pool (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Portrait of Clayton Ballou (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou crouching near pool, smoking. Description says "Sun Valley - Mar. 1950 Clayt at Lodge pool", March 1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou sitting in front of lodge. Description says "Squaw Valley - April 1950. Clayt and Junior" (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou leaning against rock wall. Description says "Log Angeles, Cal. - April 1950 Clayt at Santa Monica Beach" (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and shirtless John Roberts in front of building with stripped awning. Description reads "Squaw Vally - April 1950 Clayt + John" (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Portrait of Clayton Ballou (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou in front of house (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou on boat deck with camera (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and John Roberts holding camera on boat deck (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and John Roberts with camera (2) (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and John Roberts standing through car sunroof, with camera (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and John Roberts, filming sign roads, car in background (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and John Roberts in front of Eiffel Tower (2) (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and John Roberts in front of Eiffel tower, with camera and car (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and John Roberts standing out of car sunroof, with camera and in front of Eiffel tower (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and John Roberts reading book, microphone and camera (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou receiving an award (2) (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and man posing for photo (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and seagulls (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou in front of water (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and another man, posing in front of tree (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and another man, posing in front of tree (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and man posing next to car (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and man posing next to car (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou in sailboat (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou, holding dog, with another couple (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou sitting on couch (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and wife (?) in costumes (2) (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Portrait of Clayton Ballou (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou in front of car (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clayton Ballou and John Roberts in restaurant (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Photos of John Roberts (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Young John Roberts (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Young John Roberts in chair (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Young John Roberts next to tent (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts on back of boat, holding camera (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts in pinstriped suit, on telephone (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts editing film (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - OPortrait of John Roberts (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts drinking tea with man in navy uniform (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts in Media Corp during World War II, using large camera (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts in media corp. army uniform (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts holding teacup, with woman holding cat (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts boarding Air France plane (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts standing out of a car sunroof, with camera (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts in gondola boat, with camera (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts sitting at picnic table, in front of lodge. Verso: "Mr. Nick 962) and me at his restaurant on strela-pass. My new sweater - marron + white" (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts sitting in front of skis stuck in snow, in his "new sweater" (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts sitting with camera in lap (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts sitting in front of lodge, with camera (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts, smoking near pool. Description: "Sun Valley- Mar. 1950 John at Lodge pool" (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts, with many leis, talking with two women. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts standing at podium with microphone (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - John Roberts sitting in front of boat house. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Vacation Photos (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Teenager standing in front of concession stand (3) (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Schooner. Statsraad Lehkuhl (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - DaVinci's Inventions (20) children posing with intentions (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Disney clock tower (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Other Photos (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Children in toy truck (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Portrait of woman (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - River paddle boat (2) (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Sea plane landing (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Sea plane on water (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Sea plane on water (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Sea plane taking off (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Sea plane flying (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Sea plane and captain (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Portrait of man (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Tram to climb side of mountain (2) (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Man cleaning car (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Dog hanging out car window (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Family posing in front of car (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - A cabin in the pines, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Boardwalk (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Woman sitting on dock, large boat in background with snowcapped mountain (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Canoes lined up next to dock, with snowcapped mountains (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Sea plane on water, large boat in background with snowcapped mountains (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Train going over stone trellis (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Stone bridge, snowy landscape (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Two men playing cards (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - House with horse and buggy in front (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Abstract photo, sea plant (?)Spiderweb (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Lilly pads on pond (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Children posing for photo (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Landscape shot of people sitting on beach of lake (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Close up of phot with black background (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Beach dunes (Box 2, Folder 14)
- 7. Miscellany, 1888 - 1938
  Series contains a biographical sketch of Lowell Thomas, travel brochure items, materials from a song John Roberts wrote, and album pages from an 1888 souvenir book.
  - John's Song (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1888 Souvenir Album Pages (Box 1, Folder 23)